"How to Prevent Skin Cancer with Diet"
Millions of skin cancers
are diagnosed every year,
the most common cancer
in the United States.
I've covered the single
most important thing we can do-
protect against exposure
to UV radiation,
and just did a video
on a supplement that might help.
What about dietary protection?
The first study to elucidate
the effect of diet
on UV-induced tumors
found that high-fat diets
accelerated tumor formation
in mice.
Within six months of UV,
fifty percent of the high-fat
fed mice had tumors
compared to only 16
in the control-fed group.
Encouragingly,
switching the mice
to a low-fat diet
after the exposure
was able to negate the tumor
exacerbating high-fat effects.
In people, a dietary pattern
characterized by meat
and fat consumption
was associated
with up to a near quadrupling
of squamous cell
carcinoma risk,
the second most common type
of skin cancer,
whereas a vegetable
and fruit pattern
was associated
with a halving of risk
(apparently driven largely
by the intake of greens).
All we needed now
was to randomize people
to low-fat diets
and see if cancer
could be prevented
in people too,
and, thanks to National
Cancer Institute funding
and a Veteran Affairs
research team,
the striking results
were published
in the New England
Journal of Medicine.
Seventy-six patients
with a history of skin cancer
(and, therefore, at high risk
of developing more)
were randomized to continue
to eat their regular diets
or switch to a quote-unquote
"low-fat" diet
of 20 percent of calories
from fat.
I put low-fat in quotes
because that's actually
a high-fat diet
compared to what's normal
for our species.
For millions of years,
our ancestors may have evolved
getting approximately
10 percent
of our calories from fat.
For millions of years,
about 99.8 percent
of our time on Earth,
it was virtually impossible
for us to consume regularly
more than 10 to 15 percent
of calories as fat.
So, that's a normal fat diet
for the human species.
A low-fat diet
would be less than that.
Though 20 percent is certainly
comparatively low fat
compared to the current
adult average
in the United States
of 37 percent.
Would a drop down to 20
make a difference?
Researchers tracked
the appearance
of actinic keratoses,
rough scaly patches
that are premalignant lesions
that turn into skin cancer,
over the next two years.
The average patient
in the control group
developed 10 lesions
in those two years,
compared to just three
in the lower-fat group.
Okay, but what about
actual skin cancers?
The results were so exciting
the same team of researchers
randomized
hundreds
of skin cancer patients
to the same two diets.
By the end of the study,
the skin cancer rate
was 10 times lower
in the lower-fat group.
Now this is no clarion call
for SnackWell's cookies.
Although fat appears
twice as bad,
high-refined carb consumption
was also found to be
significantly associated
with skin wrinkling and atrophy
among a nationwide
cross-section
of middle-aged women.
Those who consistently have
higher than normal
fasting blood sugars
are perceived to be
nearly a half year older
than they really are
for every 18 points higher
their average blood sugars are.
So, those with a prediabetic
fasting blood sugar
of like 120 milligrams
per deciliter
look about a year older
than those regularly having
a normal fasting blood sugar
of around 75.
Now, the Women's Health
Initiative randomized
nearly 50,000
postmenopausal women
to a recommendation
to eat the same lower-fat diet;
yet, there was no change
in the incidence
of skin cancer.
This is not surprising
given the poor adherence.
Only 31 percent of the women
in the intervention group
complied with
the dietary recommendations.
It turns out healthy diets
may only work
if you actually eat them.